Guide to the Michael Benedikt Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Michael Benedikt papers
1951-2002
YCAL MSS 589
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.46
(4 boxes)
Collection contains correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the personal and professional life of author Michael Benedikt. Correspondence in the collection consists of letters to Benedikt from authors and artists, editors and publishers, literary agents and organizations, academic institutions, and others dating largely from the late 1950s to early 1980s. Correspondents include Duane Ackerson, Anna Balakian, Alan Brilliant, A. Poulin, Carolee Schneemann, and others. Writings feature annotated versions of early printed works by Benedikt, such as Changes (1961) and The Body (1968), printed versions of essays, and a few drafts and proofs of individual poems. Personal Papers include a curriculum vitae, electronic files, notebooks, photographs, records documenting a dispute with a New York City landlord, and other materials.
Benedikt, Michael, 1935-2007
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Asako Kitaori and Gerard Malanga, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 4 (computer disks): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Michael Benedikt (1935-2007)
Michael Benedikt was born 26 May 1935 in New York City and educated at New York University (1956) and Columbia University (1961). From the late 1950s through 1970s, Benedikt served as an editor and held teaching and writing positions at various publications and instutitions in the Northeast. He served an editor at Horizon Press (1959-1961), associate editor with Art News (1963-1972), poetry editor with the Paris Review (1974-1978), and contributing editor with the American Poetry Review. During this period he taught at Bennington (1968-1969), Sarah Lawrence (1969-1973), Hampshire (1973-1975), Vassar (1976-1977), and Boston University (1977-1979).
Benedikt's books of poetry include Changes (1961), The Body (1968), Sky (1970), Mole Notes (1971), Night Cries (1976), and The Badminton at Great Barrington (1980). Benedikt also authored plays, translations, and edited works on the theatre, and contributed poems, essays, and reviews to journals such as Poetry, American Poetry Review, Iowa Review, Massachusetts Review, Agni, Partisan Review, Ploughshares, and Tri-Quarterly. He died 27 February 2007.
Biographical information taken from "Michael Benedikt." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2001. Biography In Context. Web. 16 May 2013.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the personal and professional life of American poet and author Michael Benedikt. Correspondence in the collection consists of letters to Benedikt from authors and artists, editors and publishers, literary agents and organizations, academic institutions, and others dating largely from the late 1950s to early 1980s. Correspondents include Duane Ackerson, Anna Balakian, Alan Brilliant, A. Poulin, Carolee Schneemann, and others. Writings features annotated printed versions of early works by Benedikt, such as Changes (1961) and The Body (1968), printed versions of essays, and a few drafts and proofs of individual poems. Personal Papers include a curriculum vitae, electronic files, notebooks, photographs, records documenting a dispute with a New York City landlord, where Benedikt resided late in life, and other materials.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1957-1997. II Writings, 1951-1980. III. Personal Papers, 1968-2002.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th Century; Born digital; Electronic documents; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Ackerson, Duane, 1942-; Balakian, Anna, 1915-1997; Benedikt, Michael, 1935-2007; Brilliant, Alan; Poulin, A., Jr., 1938-1996; Schneemann, Carolee, 1939-
- Correspondence, 1957-1997; Series I; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by name.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence consists of letters to Benedikt from authors, editors and publishers, literary organizations, academic institutions, and others dating largely from the late 1950s to early 1980s.
  - Ackerson, Duane, 1997 November 5 (Box 1)
  - Balakian, Anna, 1971 May 5 (Box 1)
  - Borchardt, Georges, 1965 April 5 (Box 1)
  - Brilliant, Alan, 1966 December 24 (Box 1)
  - Hudspith, Vicki, 1978 March 6 (Box 1)
  - Kelleher, Ann, 1970-1973, undated (Box 1)
    Includes poems
  - Letters of recommendation (copies), 1975-1979 (Box 1)
  - Mussman, Toby, 1968 November 10 (Box 1)
  - New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.), 1957, 1963 (Box 1)
    Includes clippings
  - Ono, Yoko, 1971 September 28 (Box 1)
  - The Paris Review, 1981 June (Box 1)
  - Phillips, Louis, 1977 December 14 (Box 1)
  - Poetry Society of America, [1988?] September 16 (Box 1)
  - Poulin, A., 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Sarah Lawrence College, 1972-1973, undated (Box 1)
  - Schneemann, Carolee, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Stephenson, Gregory, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Treacle Press, 1979, undated (Box 1)
  - Others, 1967-1982 (Box 1)
  - Empty envelopes, 1979, undated (Box 1)
- Writings, 1951-1980; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Organized into subseries for Writings by Michael Bendikt and Writings of Others.
  Series II. Writings features annotated printed versions of early works by Benedikt, such as Changes (1961) and The Body (1968), printed versions of essays, and a few drafts and proofs of individual poems.
  - Writings by Michael Benedikt
    - " Alphaville and Its Subtext," essay, printed version, Jean-Luc Goddard, 1968 (Box 1)
    - The Badminton at Great Barrington; Or, Gustave Mahler & the Chattanooga Choo-Choo, printed version, annotated, 1980 (Box 1)
    - The Body, printed version, annotated, 1968 (Box 1)
    - "The Burning Down of Jenny's Restaurant..." proof (copy) corrected, with proofreaders' marks, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Changes, printed version, annotated, 1961 (Box 1)
    - "The Dangerous Word Dude," poem, proof (copy), corrected, with proofreaders' marks, undated (Box 1)
    - "Letter to Joan Mercury..." proof (copy), corrected, with proofreaders' marks, [1978?] (Box 1)
    - ["Naked naked as my mistress..."], poem, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1)
      Includes letter from Gerard Malanga
    - "New York: The Experimental Theatre," essay, printed version, Ambit, 1965 (Box 1)
    - "Poems," printed version, Ambit, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Sky, printed version, annotated, 1970 (Box 2)
    - "Yoko Notes," essay, printed version, art and artists, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Unidentified work, contents and drafts, typescript, undated (Box 2)
  - Writings of Others
    - Balakian, Anna
      - André Breton: Magus of Surrealism, printed version, annotated, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Carlson, Laura
      - "Brecht: Theatre as a Dialectial Organ," essay, typerscript, 1975 April (Box 2)
    - Kennedy, R. C.
      - [Introduction], typescript, 1968 July (Box 2)
    - Mallarmé, Stephane
      - Poems, printed version, annotated, 1951 (Box 2)
    - Payack, Peter
      - "How We Built the Matterhorn," printed version, 1978 (Box 2)
- Personal Papers, 1968-2002; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series III. Personal Papers include a curriculm vitae, electronic files, notebooks, photographs, records documenting a dispute with a New York City landlord, where Benedikt resided, and other materials.
  - "Business relationship between Michael Benedikt + Milton Gilman", 1980-1981, undated (Box 3)
  - Career Staffing Center application, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Curriculum vitae, [circa 1978] (Box 3)
  - Electronic files, undated; (8 computer disks)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services.
    2007-ycal-11630-0001 - 2007-ycal-11630-0008
  - Empty booklet, undated (Box 3)
  - Health records, 1988-2001, undated (Box 3)
  - Housing records, 1989 (Box 3)
  - "Landlord dispute", 2000-2002, undated; 3 (Box 3)
  - Negatives and cut film, undated (Box 3)
  - Notebooks, undated; 3 (Box 3)
  - Photographs and slide, undated; 3 (Box 3)
  - Printed ephemera, 1968-1995, undated (Box 3)
  - Sarah Lawrence college material, 1972-1973, undated (Box 3)
- Restricted Fragile Material, 0.21; (1 box)
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Computer disks, undated; (8 computer disks) (Box 4)